A Guide to the Virginia Geological Survey, Records, 1834-1903
Library of Virginia
- Series I: Correspondence of William B. Rogers, 1836-1903
  - Correspondence to William B. Rogers, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - John Sites, Rawley Springs, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, April 16, 1838, John Sites, Rawley Springs, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, asking for an analysis of Rawley Springs water and describing the characteristics of a new spring he had discovered last fall. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - E. Foreman, Baltimore, Maryland, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, April 16, 1838, E. Foreman, Baltimore, Maryland, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, asking for a response to his earlier letter seeking employment. 2 pp. with address leaf.
    - J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, April 18, 1838, J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, discussing amounts due and amounts already paid to Rogers and his assistants in salary and stating that only 1,000 copies of Rogers's report will be printed. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, April 24, 1838, George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging his receipt of and response to a letter from Rogers and stating that he is prepared to accept Rogers's original offer of employment. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, April 30, 1838, George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, mentioning letters which apparently crossed in the mail and repeating his acceptance of Rogers's original offer. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - Broadside. Medical College of Richmond, Virginia. Winter term of lectures, May 1, 1838, Broadside. Medical College of Richmond, Virginia. Winter term of lectures ... [list of faculty and information on term to begin November 5, 1838, of the medical department of Hampden-Sydney College] Aug. L. Warner, M.D., Dean of the Faculty. 1 p. with address leaf to Dr. Rogers, University of Virginia.
    - George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 2, 1838, George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of Rogers's letters of April 25 and 27, informing him that he will leave New York by May 6 and giving instructions as to where to direct mail to him in Virginia. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Hot Springs, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 9, 1838, W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Hot Springs, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, thanking him for sending a check; discussing his financial needs; describing his geological observations in the neighborhood of Fincastle; and mentioning his plans to visit Catawba Iron Works. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - E[ben] N. Hosford (?), Troy, New York, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 14, 1838, E[ben] N. Hosford (?), Troy, New York, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, referring to an earlier letter to Rogers seeking employment and to an expected response from Rogers which probably had miscarried and informing Rogers that since he has been induced to take the position in New York vacated by George W. Boyd, he will not be able to work with Rogers this summer but would like to be taken on the following summer if the opportunity is available. 2 pp. with address leaf. Eben Norton Horsford (?) (July 27, 1818-January 1, 1893), chemist, graduated from Rensselaer (?) Polytechnic Institute in 1838, then worked on the New York State Natural History Survey. After further study in Germany, 1844-1847, he introduced European chemical knowledge and methods to America at Harvard and later made a fortune in Rumford Chemical Company.
    - J[ames] Brown, Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 18, 1838, J[ames] Brown, Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, mentioning amounts deposited in the Bank of Virginia to Rogers's and William E. A. Aikin's credit, describing the fiscal problems of the geological survey, and speculating upon the likelihood of the General Assembly's dropping the survey from the budget. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Lafayette, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 17, 1838, W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Lafayette, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing a peculiar conglomerate found on McAfee's Knob on Catawba Mountain; mentioning a box of specimens he sent from Catawba Iron Works and a box of speciments from the foot of North Mountain; reporting on plaster dug near Buford's Gap; and outlining his plans to proceed through Salem, Lafayette, Montgomery Courthouse, and Christiansburg. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - C[harles] B. Hayden, Sweet Springs, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 19, 1838, C[harles] B. Hayden, Sweet Springs, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, informing him that he was unable to inspect a fault line because the letter from Rogers instructing him to do so arrived too late; describing his geological investigations around Covington and Callaghan's and Peters Mountain; discussing his plans to continue along the western side of Peters Mountain; and commenting on the general business of the survey and on his financial problems. 6 pp. with address leaf.
    - C[harles] B. Hayden, Grey Sulphur, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 23, [1838], C[harles] B. Hayden, Grey Sulphur, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, stating his disappointment in finding no mail waiting for him; reporting on the geology of Peters Mountain; and announcing his plans to proceed to Callaghan's. 2 pp. with address leaf.
    - John Sites, Rawley Springs, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 26, 1838, John Sites, Rawley Springs, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, asking for the analysis of the Rawley Springs water which he wants to publish. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - J. W. Dibrell, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 26, 1838, J. W. Dibrell, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, giving a description of Daggers Springs in Botetourt County, their location, and several routes to get to them and complaining about his financial misfortunes. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Newbern, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 26, 1838, W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Newbern, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing his procedures and the results of his analysis of a sample of Yellow Springs water through evaporation and the collection of residue; mentioning a box of specimens sent to Lynchburg; describing plans to go to Wythe Courthouse by way of the Lead Mines; and complaining of financial problems. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - J[ames] Brown, Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 29, 1838, J[ames] Brown, Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning funds deposited to the account of James B. Rogers, and commenting on an address Rogers had given. 1 p. with address leaf. James Blythe Rogers (February 11, 1802-June 15, 1852), chemist, brother of William Barton Rogers, was best known for his contributions to the development of methods of chemical analysis. He was appointed assistant geologist by the Board of Public Works in May 1837. He resigned in April 1840 and was reappointed assistant geologist by the Board of Public Works on May 1, 1841.
    - William Seymour, Moorefield, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 30, 1838, William Seymour, Moorefield, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, asking for the results of the chemical analysis of water from Howard's Lick Spring. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - Samuel McCamant, Grayson Courthouse, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 3, 1838, Samuel McCamant, Grayson Courthouse, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, asking for the results of the chemical analysis of spring water for the Grayson Sulphur Springs Company. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Saltville, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 11, 1838, W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Saltville, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning the breaking down of his horses; describing the geology of the Macks Mountains and Dry Run Gap; discussing the contents of a specimen box; and mentioning the roads made almost impossible by rain. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - C[harles] B. Hayden, Seyberts, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 17, [1838], C[harles] B. Hayden, Seyberts, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing his recent travels; complaining of the lack of mail from Rogers; discussing his financial problems; and describing the geology around Augusta Springs. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - James B. Rogers, White Sulphur [Springs], to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 20, 1838, James B. Rogers, White Sulphur [Springs], Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, explaining the problems resulting from his having forgotten some weights for use in chemical analysis; giving the analysis of some spring water and describing the methods used to obtain it; mentioning plans to depart for the Blue Sulphur Springs; discussing the geology of Augusta Springs; describing a meeting with Dr. Daubeny; and referring to the state of his own health. 3 pp. with address leaf. Charles Giles Bridle Daubeny (February 11, 1795-December 13, 1867), M.D., F.R.S., was professor of chemistry and botany at Oxford University.
    - James B. Rogers, Blue Sulphur [Springs], to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 26, 1838, James B. Rogers, Blue Sulphur [Springs], to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, expressing his concern about not receiving a letter from him; giving an analysis of Blue Sulphur Springs water; asking for instructions on how to proceed at the Salt and Red Sulphur Springs and a question about sandstone found on Muddy Creek Mountain; amd stating his immediate plans for collecting samples. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Tazewell Court House, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 27, 1838, W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Tazewell Court House, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing his travels of the last ten days in eastern Tazewell County, in particular the geology of Abbs Valley; outlining his plans to proceed to Russell County in hope of meeting with General Johnson there; and mentioning financial matters. 4 pp.
    - William Robertson, Jr., Salt Sulphur Springs, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, July 3, 1838, William Robertson, Jr., Salt Sulphur Springs, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing a new spring opened by Erskine and Caruthers, informing him of the imminent arrival of a sample of water from it; and requesting an analysis as soon as convenient. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - Stephen Grubs, Nineveh, Frederick County, to James B. Rogers, University of [Virginia], July 7, 1838, Stephen Grubs, Nineveh, Frederick County, to James B. Rogers, University of [Virginia], writing Rogers to call upon him on his next trip to the area, as he knows more about minerals in the area and has more samples in his possession than anyone else in the vicinity. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - James B. Rogers, Blue Sulphur [Springs], to William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, July 9, 1838, James B. Rogers, Blue Sulphur [Springs], to William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, giving an analysis of old and new springs there; describing the geology of the Crows Ferry-Sweet Springs region; and asking for information concerning his family. 4 pp.
    - W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Russell Court House, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, July 10, 1838, W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Russell Court House, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, thanking him for his recent letters; discussing their proposed excursion down Guyandotte River; complaining about the local food; and mentioning samples sent by way of Lynchburg. 4 pp.
    - W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Osborn's Ford, Scott County, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, July 19, 1838, W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Osborn's Ford, Scott County, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the geology of Russell County and his plan to explore Scott and Lee Counties. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - James B. Rogers, Pearisburg, to William B. Rogers, Fincastle, July 23, 1838, James B. Rogers, Pearisburg, to William B. Rogers, Fincastle, describing the geology of the New River Gap and Peters Mountain area and hoping to see him in Fincastle. 2 pp. with address leaf.
    - R. H. Toler, J. N. Brooks, and William S. Reid, Jr., Lynchburg, to William B. Rogers, [Lynchburg], July 21, 1838, R. H. Toler, J. N. Brooks, and William S. Reid, Jr., Lynchburg, to William B. Rogers, [Lynchburg], thanking him on behalf of the Lynchburg Young Men's Society for the lecture "delivered before them this evening," and requesting a copy for publication. 1 pp. with address leaf.
    - W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Cove Creek, Scott County, to [William B. Rogers], n.p., July 26, 1838, W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Cove Creek, Scott County, to [William B. Rogers], n.p., expressing surprise that Rogers had not received his earlier letters; describing his work between New River and Cove Creek; outlining his plans for exploring Tazewell and Mercer counties and Abbs Valley; and discussing the geology of Little Stoney Creek, the Clinch Mountain area, and the Powell's Valley vicinity. 4 pp., incomplete.
    - [William B. Rogers], Fincastle, to "Dear Sir" [Lynchburg Young Men's Society, Lynchburg], July 27, 1838, [William B. Rogers], Fincastle, to "Dear Sir" [Lynchburg Young Men's Society, Lynchburg], regretting that he left Lynchburg in such haste that he forgot to reply "in form" to the request of the society. 1 p., incomplete.
    - W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Scott Court House, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, August 12, 1838, W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Scott Court House, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing his work in Scott and Washington counties and the family problems which will require him to return to Baltimore in mid-October; discussing the geology of Lee County; and mentioning his trouble with his horses and servant. 4 pp.
    - C[harles] B. Hayden, Hedgesville, Berkeley County, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, August 25, 1838, C[harles] B. Hayden, Hedgesville, Berkeley County, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing what remains to be done in the area; discussing the hot and bug-infested mountains; mentioning smome varieties of slate he has seen; and disagreeing with Rogers about olive slate alleged to exist between Little and Big Timber Ridge. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - George W. Boyd, Waynesboro, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, September 10, 1838, George W. Boyd, Waynesboro, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of Rogers's letter of September 8 and presenting a day by day account of his travels and observations of the geology of the mountains around Lexington and the Tye River Gap. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - George W. Boyd, Luray, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, September 19 and 20, 1838, George W. Boyd, Luray, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing his route from Waynesboro to Luray; mentioning a two to three week old forest fire still burning near Brown's Gap and his visit to the Shenandoah Iron Works; and charting the relationship between the temperature at which water boils and varous altitudes in the Blue Ridge. 2 pp. with address leaf.
    - George W. Boyd, University of Virginia, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, September 22, 1838, George W. Boyd, University of Virginia, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, mentioning a visit to Blackford's iron furnace and describing a ride up Stony Manpeak and the greenstone and various minerals found there. 2 pp. with address leaf.
    - George W. Boyd, University of Virginia, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, October 27, 1838, George W. Boyd, University of Virginia, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, stating that he had left specimens under the dining room table in a champagne bucket and noting other details for Rogers's benefit in concluding the season's work on the survey. 1 pp. with address leaf.
  - Correspondence to William B. Rogers, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, February 3, 1839, J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of Rogers's letters of January 13 and 29; discussing financial matters, particularly those of Dr. [William E. A.] Aikin; speculating on the possibility that the General Assembly will suspend the continuation of the survey, and giving Aikin's account current with the state and with Rogers. 2 pp. with address leaf.
    - George W. Boyd, New York, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, March 20, 1839, George W. Boyd, New York, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, relating that on his way north he had seen both Henry D. Rogers and Robert Rogers in Philadelphia; giving prices for certain chemicals; presenting his plans for returning to Virginia in April; discussing mineral specimens he plans to bring; reviewing sarcastically a recent article concerning red sandstone; and mentioning a new book on silurian rocks. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - William E. A. Aikin, Baltimore, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, April 13, 1839, William E. A. Aikin, Baltimore, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, informing him that he must resign from the survey because he has been appointed Governor of the Infirmary at the University of Maryland, a position which requires his continuous presence. 2 pp.
    - J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to [William B.] Rogers, University of Virginia, April 15, 1839, J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to [William B.] Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning financial matters; informing him that his reports have been printed and are at hand; and a postscript expressing his regrets over Rogers's having been thrown from a carriage and urging him not to overwork. 2 pp. with address leaf.
    - [William B. Rogers], University of Virginia, to "Dear Henry" [D. Robers], n.p., April 17, 1839, [William B. Rogers], University of Virginia, to "Dear Henry" [D. Robers], n.p., reporting on the "results of my experiments in regard to the composition and hydraulic character of our secondary limestones ... with an account of the method [used to separate] the magnesia and lime." 3 pp., incomplete [draft].
    - James B. Rogers, Millborough, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 15, 1838, James B. Rogers, Millborough, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, referring to his lame horse; describing the geology of Panther Gap and Buffalo Gap; detailing his plans to proceed through Clifton Forge to the vicinity of Rich Patch; and discussing his need of a dentist. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - [William B. Rogers], University of Virginia, to [Caleb Briggs], n.p., April 20, 1839, [William B. Rogers], University of Virginia, to [Caleb Briggs], n.p., offering him a position as assistant geologist, in place of Aikin, and describing the requirements of the job. 3 pp., incomplete.
    - George W. Boyd, Scottsville, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, April 28, 1839, George W. Boyd, Scottsville, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the geology of the country between Charlottesville and Scottsville and between Scottsville and Warren along the James River and Kanawha Canal; reporting on some durable sandstone found at Green Mountain twelve miles west of Scottsville; and mentioning iron ore found at Scottsville. 2 pp. with address leaf.
    - Caleb Briggs, Jr., New York, New York, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, April 28, 1839, Caleb Briggs, Jr., New York, New York, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, accepting the offer of the position of assistant geologist; explaining the necessity of his visiting Boston and Ohio before coming to Virginia; stating his experience as head of the chemistry and natural history department at Rensellaer (sp.?) Polytechnic Institute and as assistant geologist on the geological surveys of New York and Ohio; and inquiring about a position on the faculty of Emory and Henry College. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - George W. Boyd, Lynchburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 12, 1839, George W. Boyd, Lynchburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing his travels and the geology of the country between Scottsville and New Market, in the vicinity of New Market, between New Market and Warminster, and between Warminster and Maysville. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - George W. Boyd, Maysville, Buckingham County, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 19, 1839, George W. Boyd, Maysville, Buckingham County, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the geology of the country between Maysville and Lynchburg and discussing the Buckingham County gold mines. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - I[srael] Slade, Wythe County, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 21 and 22, 1839, I[srael] Slade, Wythe County, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning his analysis of the limestone of Blacksburg, Christiansburg, Newbern, Robison's Tract, and Little Walkers Mountain and asking for further instructions. 7 pp. with address leaf.
    - James B. Rogers, White Sulphur [Springs], to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 23, 1838, James B. Rogers, White Sulphur [Springs], to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning his lame horse, Dragon, and accusing William E. A. Aikin of mistreating him; presenting extracts from his notes describing Panther Gap, the gap at Clifton Forge, Brands Mountain, and Falling Spring Valley; and discussing the new construction at White Sulphur Springs. 8 pp.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Albany, New York, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 24, 1839, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Albany, New York, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of Rogers's letter of May 13; enclosing a testimonial letter from Professor [Amos] Eaton [sent to Board of Public Works by Rogers and returned to Briggs on July 21, 1843, at his request]; and asking for further instructions. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - George W. Boyd, Maysville, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 26, 1839, George W. Boyd, Maysville, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning the geology of Buckingham, Cumberland, and Prince Edward counties; discussing his lack of funds; and listing the contents of four boxes of specimens. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - Broadside. Western Enquirer, Lewisburg, Virginia. To the Publick. White Sulphur Springs, Greenbrier County, Va. May 31, 1839, Broadside. Western Enquirer, Lewisburg, Virginia. To the Publick. White Sulphur Springs, Greenbrier County, Va. [Testimonials as to the storage and keeping quality of water from the springs.] On reverse: Prof. Wm. B. Rogers, University, Va. 1 p.